Finding Aid for Grand Rapids Chamber of Commerce records, 1887-1946
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Grand Rapids Chamber of Commerce records
1887-1946
Grand Rapids Chamber of Commerce (Mich.)
88371 Bm Microcopy
Board of directors minutes, committee minutes and reports, and newsletters; include materials concerning the Chamber's efforts on behalf of civic and local economic improvements.
17 microfilms
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The Grand Rapids Chamber of Commerce (donor no. 5899 ) made these records available for microfilming in 1976 prior to their being deposited with the Grand Rapids Public Library.
Periodic additions to the records are not expected.
The record group is open to research.
The original materials are located at the Grand Rapids Public Library.
The Grand Rapids Chamber of Commerce was founded in 1887 under the name of the Board of Trade. Since its founding, the organization has attempted both to improve Grand Rapids and to promote the advantages of the city to non-residents. Though the organization's primary interest has been in improving business conditions, the Chamber has taken a very broad view about what makes a community desirable to business. Thus, the records of the organization show the Chamber involved in a whole series of activities, including education, public health, governmental organization and efficiency, transportation, housing, public welfare, literally everything from railroad freight rates to the Christmas decorations placed in the downtown area.
This microfilm edition of the records of the Grand Rapids Chamber of Commerce covers the years 1887 to 1946 and includes board of directors minutes, committee minutes and reports, newsletters and other material documenting the Chamber's efforts on behalf of civic and local economic improvements. The microfilmed records are organized into six series: Early Records; Minutes of the Directors' Meetings; Miscellaneous Committee Minutes; Miscellaneous Committee Reports; Committee of 100; and Newsletters.
Subjects:
Boards of trade--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; Grand Rapids (Mich.)--History.
- Early records
  Early records includes the charter agreement and two record books (labeled no. 2 and no. 3). Record book no. 1 has been lost. The remaining record books cover the period 1895 to 1908 and combine together in chronological order both committee and directors minutes.
  - Charter Agreement, 1887 (Reel 1)
  - Record Book no. 2, 1895-1905 (Reel 1)
  - Record Book no. 3, 1905-1908 (Reel 1)
- Minutes of the Directors' Meetings
  Beginning in 1909, the minutes of the chamber's committees and board of directors were separated. The second series of the collection comprises the board of directors minutes, 1909-1946.
  - Vol. 1, 1909-1910 (Reel 1)
  - Vol. 2, 1910-1911 (Reel 1)
  - Vol. 3, 1911-1912 (Reel 1)
  - Vol. 4, 1912-1913 (Reel 1)
  - Vol. 5, 1913 (Reel 1)
  - Vol. 6, 1914-1915 (Reel 1)
  - Vol. 7, 1915-1917 (Reel 2)
  - Vol. 8, 1917-1919 (Reel 2)
  - Vol. 9, 1919-1922 (Reel 2)
  - Vol. 10, 1922-1926 (Reel 2)
  - Vol. 11, 1926-1930 (Reel 3)
  - Vol. 12, 1930 (Reel 3)
  - Vol. 13, 1931 (Reel 3)
  - Vol. 14, 1932 (Reel 3)
  - Vol. 15, 1933 (Reel 4)
  - Vol. 16, 1934 (Reel 4)
  - Vol. 17, 1935 (Reel 4)
  - Vol. 18, 1936 (Reel 4)
  - Vol. 19, 1937 (Reel 5)
  - Vol. 20, 1938 (Reel 5)
  - Vol. 21, 1939 (Reel 5)
  - Vol. 22, 1940 (Reel 5)
  - Vol. 23, 1941 (Reel 5)
  - Vol. 24, 1942 (Reel 6)
  - Vol. 25, 1943 (Reel 6)
  - Vol. 26, 1944 (Reel 6)
  - Vol. 27, 1945 (Reel 6)
  - Vol. 28, 1946 (Reel 6)
- Miscellaneous Committee Minutes
  The manner in which these committee minutes of the various chamber committees were bound for 1909 to 1929 is extremely disorganized. After 1929, however, and running up through 1946, the committee minutes and reports have been bound chronologically. Both director and committee minute books frequently contain a fairly complete index which was compiled at the time the records were being gathered for binding. When available, these indices appear at the beginning of each volume.
  - 1903-1905 (Reel 7)
  - 1905-1907 (Reel 7)
  - 1907-1909 (Reel 7)
  - 1909 (Reel 7)
  - March 3, 1909-July 28, 1911 (Reel 8)
  - March 24, 1909-July 7, 1911 (Reel 8)
  - December 8, 1911-March 11, 1915 (Reel 8)
  - October 5, 1912-February 8, 1917 (Reel 8)
  - January 8, 1915-February 1, 1917 (Reel 8)
  - December 13, 1916-December 16, 1925 (Reel 9)
  - January 3, 1917-December 30, 1918 (Reel 9)
  - May 9, 1918-December 2, 1929 (Reel 9)
  - November 25, 1925-December 31, 1929 (Reel 9)
  - January 8, 1926-January 3, 1930 (Reel 9)
  - 1930 (Reel 10)
  - 1931 (Reel 10)
  - 1932 (Reel 10)
  - 1933 (Reel 10)
- Miscellaneous Committee Reports
  The Committee Reports date from 1934 to 1946.
  - 1934 (Reel 11)
  - 1935 (Reel 11)
  - 1936 (Reel 11)
  - 1937 (Reel 12)
  - 1938 (Reel 12)
  - 1939 (Reel 12)
  - 1940 (Reel 13)
  - 1941 (Reel 13)
  - 1942 (Reel 13)
  - 1943 (Reel 13)
  - 1944 (Reel 14)
  - 1945 (Reel 14)
  - 1946 (Reel 14)
- Committee of 100
  - 1909-1911 (Reel 14)
- Newsletters of Chamber of Commerce
  This newsletter appeared under various titles and are of varying historical value. After 1931, the publication was but four pages and included a limited amount of information.
  - Progress
    - 1918 (Reel 15)
    - 1919 (Reel 15)
    - 1920 (Reel 15)
    - 1921 (Reel 15)
    - 1922 (Reel 15)
  - Spectator
    - 1927 (Reel 15)
    - 1928 (Reel 16)
    - 1929 (Reel 16)
    - 1930 (Reel 16)
    - 1931 (Reel 17)
  - News Bulletin
    - 1932 (Reel 17)
    - 1933 (Reel 17)
    - 1934 (Reel 17)
    - 1935 (Reel 17)
    - 1936 (Reel 17)
    - 1937 (Reel 17)
    - 1938 (Reel 17)
    - 1939 (Reel 17)
    - 1940 (Reel 17)
    - 1941 (Reel 17)
    - 1942 (Reel 17)
    - 1943 (Reel 17)
    - 1944 (Reel 17)
    - 1945 (Reel 17)
    - 1946 (Reel 17)